{"author": "Robert R. Harr","data": [{"chapter": "2.3","questions": [{"data": [{"choices": ["Factor VII", "Factor X", "PF3", "Calcium"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Factor X","explanation": "The APTT is sensitive to the deficiency of coagulation factors in the intrinsic pathway (factors XII, XI, IX, and VIII) and the common pathway (factors X, V, II, and I)"},"question": "The APTT is sensitive to a deficiency of which clotting factor?","reference": "Hemostasis/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/Factor deficiency/2"},{"choices": ["TT", "APTT", "PT", "Immunologic fibrinogen level"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Immunologic fibrinogen level","explanation": "The level of plasma fibrinogen determined immunologically is normal. In a patient with dysfibrinogenemia, fibrinogen is not polymerized properly, causing abnormal results of the fibrinogen-dependent coagulation tests"},"question": "Which test result would be normal in a patient with dysfibrinogenemia?","reference": "Hemostasis/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Factor deficiency/2"},{"choices": ["Necrotic liver disease","Factor X deficiency","Fibrinogen deficiency","Obstructive jaundice"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Obstructive jaundice","explanation": "Obstructive jaundice contributes to coagulation disorders by preventing vitamin K absorption. Vitamin K is fat soluble and requires bile salts for absorption. Parenteral administration of vitamin K bypasses the bowel, hence the need for bile salts"},"question": "A patient with a prolonged PT is given intravenous vitamin K. PT is corrected to normal after 24 hours. Which clinical condition most likely caused these results?","reference": "Hemostasis/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Vitamin K deficiency/3"},{"choices": ["Factor X", "Factor VIII", "Factor IX", "Factor XI"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Factor X","explanation": "Factor X, a common pathway factor deficiency, is most likely suspected because both PT and APTT are prolonged. Other causes may include liver disease, vitamin K deficiency, and anticoagulant drugs, such as warfarin and heparin"},"question": "Which factor deficiency is associated with prolonged PT and APTT?","reference": "Hemostasis/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/Factor deficiency/2"},{"choices": ["Factor V", "Factor VIII", "Factor IX", "Factor X"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Factor IX","explanation": "Because prolonged APTT is not corrected with factor IX–deficient plasma, factor IX is suspected to be deficient in the test plasma"},"question": "Prolonged APTT is corrected with factor VIII–deficient plasma but not with factor IX– deficient plasma. Which factor is deficient?","reference": "Hemostasis/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/Factor deficiency/3"},{"choices": ["Abnormal PLT aggregation","Autosomal recessive inheritance","Mild to severe bleeding episodes","Prolonged PT"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Mild to severe bleeding episodes","explanation": "Hemophilia A (factor VIII deficiency) is characterized by mild to severe bleeding episodes, depending on the concentration of factor VIII:C. Hemophilia A is inherited as a sex-linked disease. PLT aggregation and PT are both normal in hemophilia A"},"question": "Which of the following is a characteristic of classic hemophilia A?","reference": "Hemostasis/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Hemostasis/Hemophilia/2"},{"choices": ["Factor VIII deficiency","von Willebrand disease","DIC","Factor IX deficiency"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "DIC","explanation": "In DIC, there is a diffuse intravascular generation of thrombin and fibrin. As a result, clotting factors and PLTs are consumed, resulting in decreased PLT count and increased PT and APTT"},"question": "Refer to the following results: PT = prolonged APTT = prolonged PLT count = decreased Which disorder may be indicated?","reference": "Hemostasis/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Coagulation disorders/3"},{"choices": ["Adenocarcinoma","Idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP)","Post transfusion purpura (PTP)","Heparin-induced thrombocytopenia (HIT)"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Adenocarcinoma","explanation": "Adenocarcinoma can liberate procoagulant (thromboplastic) substances that can activate prothrombin intravascularly. ITP is a thrombocytopenia caused by an autoantibody; PTP is an alloimmune thrombocytopenia caused by transfusion of blood or blood products; HIT results from an antibody to heparin–PF4 complex causing thrombocytopenia in 1% to 5% of patients who are on heparin therapy. In some affected persons, thrombosis may also occur"},"question": "Which of the following is a predisposing condition for the development of DIC?","reference": "Hemostasis/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/DIC/1"},{"choices": ["Bleeding episodes","Epistaxis","Decreased risk of thrombosis","Increased risk of thrombosis"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Increased risk of thrombosis","explanation": "Factor XII–deficient patients commonly have thrombotic episodes. In vitro, activated factor XII (XIIa) activates factor XI to factor XIa. In vivo, however, factor XII plays a major role in the fibrinolytic system by activating plasminogen to form plasmin. Hemorrhagic manifestations are not associated with factor XII deficiency because VIIa/TF can activate factor IX to factor IXa and factor X to factor Xa to generate thrombin"},"question": "Factor XII deficiency is associated with:","reference": "Hemostasis/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Factor deficiency/2"},{"choices": ["Hemophilia A","Bernard–Soulier syndrome","von Willebrand disease","Glanzmann thrombasthenia"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Hemophilia A","explanation": "Hemophilia A is associated with deficiency of factor VIII, resulting in bleeding and abnormal APTT. The PLT number and function are normal in this disorder. Von Willebrand disease is a disorder of PLT adhesion associated with decreased VWF and factor VIII, causing an abnormal PLT function test result and abnormal APTT. Both Glanzmann thrombasthenia and Bernard–Soulier syndrome cause abnormal PLT aggregation but do not cause abnormal APTT"},"question": "The following results were obtained on a patient: normal PLT count and function, normal PT, and prolonged APTT. Which of the following disorders is most consistent with these results?","reference": "Hemostasis/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Coagulation disorders/3"},{"choices": ["Factor VII deficiency","Factor VIII deficiency","Factor X deficiency","Hypofibrinogenemia"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Hypofibrinogenemia","explanation": "Fibrinogen (factor I) is a clotting protein of the common pathway and is evaluated by TT. In hypofibrinogenemia (fibrinogen concentration less than 100 mg/dL), PT, APTT, and TT are prolonged. In factor VII deficiency, APTT is normal; in factor VIII deficiency, PT is normal; and in factor X deficiency, TT is normal"},"question": "The following laboratory results were obtained from a 40-year-old woman: PT = 20 sec; APTT = 50 sec; TT = 18 sec. What is the most probable diagnosis?","reference": "Hemostasis/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Factor deficiency/3"},{"choices": ["Normal patient plasma","Factor VIII–deficient plasma","Plasma with a high concentration of factor VIII","Normal control plasma"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Factor VIII–deficient plasma","explanation": "Coagulation factor assays are based on the ability of the patient’s plasma to correct any specific factor–deficient plasma. To measure for factor VIII activity in a patient’s plasma, diluted patient plasma is mixed with factor VIII–deficient plasma. The APTT test is performed on the mixture. Each laboratory should calculate its own normal ranges, which are based on the patient population, reagents, and instrument used. A range of 50% to 150% is considered normal"},"question": "When performing a factor VIII activity assay, a patient’s plasma is mixed with:","reference": "Hemostasis/Apply principles of basic laboratory procedures/Factor assay/2"},{"choices": ["Fresh frozen plasma (FFP)","Factor VIII concentrate","Prothrombin complex concentrate","Factor V Leiden"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Factor VIII concentrate","explanation": "Factor VIII concentrate (human or recombinant) is the treatment of choice for patients with factor VIII deficiency. FFP contains factor VIII; however, it is no longer used as the primary treatment for factor VIII deficiency. Prothrombin complex concentrate is used to treat patients with factor VIII inhibitor"},"question": "The most suitable product for treatment of factor VIII deficiency is:","reference": "Hemostasis/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Treatment/2"},{"choices": ["Factor VIII deficiency","Factor VIII inhibitor","Lupus anticoagulant","Afibrinogenemia"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Afibrinogenemia","explanation": "Fibrinogen is a plasma protein that is essential for PLT aggregation as well as fibrin formation. In afibrinogenemia, PLT aggregation is abnormal"},"question": "Which of the following is associated with an abnormal PLT aggregation test result?","reference": "Hemostasis/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Factor deficiency/2"},{"choices": ["Factor VIII deficiency","DIC","von Willebrand disease","Factor IX deficiency"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "von Willebrand disease","explanation": "VWF is involved in both PLT adhesion and coagulation via complexing with factor VIII. Therefore, in von Willebrand disease (deficiency or functional abnormality of VWF) factor VIII is also decreased, causing abnormal APTT as well as abnormal PLT aggregation to ristocetin. The PLT count and PT are not affected in VWF deficiency"},"question": "Refer to the following results: PT = normal APTT = prolonged PLT count = normal PLT aggregation to ristocetin = abnormal Which of the following disorders may be indicated?","reference": "Hemostasis/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Coagulation disorders/3"},{"choices": ["Prolonged APTT, normal PT","Prolonged PT and APTT","Prolonged PT, normal APTT","Normal PT and APTT"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Prolonged APTT, normal PT","explanation": "Hemophilia A is associated with factor VIII deficiency. Factor VIII is a factor in the intrinsic coagulation pathway that is evaluated by the APTT test and not the PT test. The PT test evaluates the extrinsic and common pathways"},"question": "Which results are associated with hemophilia A?","reference": "Hemostasis/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Hemophilia/2"},{"choices": ["Primary fibrinolysis","DIC","Factor VIII deficiency","Fibrinogen deficiency"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "DIC","explanation": "Increased fibrin monomers result from coagulation activation. DIC is an acquired condition associated with spontaneous activation of coagulation and fibrinolysis. In primary fibrinolysis, the fibrinolytic system is activated, and fibrin monomers are normal"},"question": "Fibrin monomers are increased in which of the following conditions?","reference": "Hemostasis/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/2"},{"choices": ["An inherited disorder of coagulation","Severe liver disease","Dysfibrinogenemia","Lupus anticoagulant"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Severe liver disease","explanation": "Most of the clotting factors are made in the liver. Therefore, severe liver disease results in multiple-factor deficiencies. An inherited disorder of coagulation is commonly associated with a single-factor deficiency. Lupus anticoagulant is directed against the phospholipid-dependent coagulation factors. Dysfibrinogenemia results from an abnormal fibrinogen molecule"},"question": "Which of the following is associated with multiple factor deficiencies?","reference": "Hemostasis/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Factor deficiency/2"},{"choices": ["Factor VII deficiency","Factor VIII deficiency","Factor XII deficiency","Factor XIII deficiency"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Factor XIII deficiency","explanation": "Factor XIII deficiency can lead to impaired wound healing and may cause severe bleeding problems. Factor XIII is a fibrin stabilizing factor that changes the fibrinogen bonds in fibrin polymers to stable covalent bonds. Factor XIII is not involved in the process of fibrin formation and, therefore, PT and APTT are both normal"},"question": "Normal PT and APTT results in a patient with poor wound healing may be associated with:","reference": "Hemostasis/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Factor deficiency/2"},{"choices": ["Bleeding","Thrombosis","Thrombocytopenia","Thrombocytosis"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Thrombosis","explanation": "Fletcher factor (prekallikrein) is referred to as a contact factor. Activated prekallikrein is named kallikrein. In vitro, kallikrein is involved in activation of factor XI to XIa causing prolonged APTT. In vivo, it plays a role in the fibrinolytic system and, similar to factor XII deficiency, Fletcher factor deficiency may be associated with thrombosis"},"question": "Fletcher factor (prekallikrein) deficiency may be associated with:","reference": "Hemostasis/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Factor deficiency/2"},{"choices": ["Hemarthrosis","Mucous membrane bleeding","Mild bleeding during surgery","Immune-mediated thrombocytopenia"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Hemarthrosis","explanation": "In severe hemophilia A, factor VIII activity is less than 1%, resulting in a severe bleeding diathesis, such as hemarthrosis (bleeding into the joints)"},"question": "One of the complications associated with a severe hemophilia A is:","reference": "Hemostasis/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Hemophilia/1"},{"choices": ["Type 1", "Type 2A", "Type 2B", "Type 3"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Type 1","explanation": "VWF is a multimeric plasma glycoprotein that results in different subtypes of von Willebrand disease with varied severity. The most common subtype is subtype 1, and 70% to 80% of these cases are associated with mild bleeding. Subtype 3 involves the total absence of the von Willebrand molecule and is associated with severe bleeding. Subtypes 2A and 2B result in deficiency of intermediate- and/or high-molecular- weight portions of the von Willebrand molecule and are associated with 10% to 12% and 3% to 6% of cases of von Willebrand disease, respectively"},"question": "The most common subtype of classic von Willebrand disease is:","reference": "Hemostasis/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/von Willebrand disease/2"},{"choices": ["Factor VIII", "Factor V", "Factor XI", "Factor IX"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Factor V","explanation": "Factor V (common pathway factor) deficiency is most likely suspected because both PT and APTT are prolonged, and both are corrected when mixed with normal plasma"},"question": "Prolonged APTT and PT are corrected when mixed with normal plasma. Which factor is most likely deficient?","reference": "Hemostasis/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/Factor deficiency/3"}],"type": "MULTIPLE_CHOICE"}],"topic": "Coagulation System Disorders"}],"edition": "5th","title": "Medical Laboratory Science Review"}